Guide to the Jerome K. and Ora Engelberg Percus Papers MC.364
New York University Archives
Jerome K. and Ora Engelberg Percus Papers
1933-2021
New York University Archives
Percus, Jerome K. (Jerome Kenneth)
Percus, Ora E.
Percus, Allon
MC.364
69.5 Linear Feet in 139 manuscript boxes, 1 small flat box, 1 small box, and 2 oversize folders in shared housing
Jerome K. Percus (1926-2021) was a physicist and mathematician who taught in both the NYU Departments of Mathematics and Physics and spent the majority of his academic career at NYU. His research and teaching focused on many-body systems, statistical and mathematical physics, biophysics, chemical physics, and mathematical biology. Ora Engelberg Percus was a mathematician who taught as an adjunct professor in the NYU Department of Mathematics, in addition to her previous teaching positions at the University of Tel Aviv, Columbia University's Teachers College, and City College (CUNY). Her primary research interests included many-body systems, probability and queueing theory, and random number generators. The Jerome K. and Ora Engelberg Percus Papers (dated 1933-2021) consist of materials documenting the academic careers of Jerome K. Percus and Ora Engelberg Percus. Materials in this collection include correspondence; college and graduate school coursework; research files, including data and calculations; original writings in various stages of completion; teaching files, including course materials and lecture notes; grant proposals and other project files; and conference presentations. Materials documenting Jerome and Ora's original research represent their scholarly outputs, both as individuals and as collaborators who often co-authored work together. This collection also documents Ora Engelberg Percus' experiences as a woman in the male-dominated field of mathematics. Correspondence, resumes, and legal filings document her tenure denial at City College, CUNY's policy in the 1970s of required unpaid maternity leave, her claims of gender discrimination for being dismissed while pregnant, and her participation in the Melani v. CUNY lawsuit. The collection also includes materials documenting Jerome K. Percus' early life, including childhood drawings, photographs, and school yearbooks.
Scope and Contents
The Jerome K. and Ora Engelberg Percus Papers (dated 1933-2021) consists of materials documenting the academic careers of Jerome K. Percus, who taught physics and mathematics at NYU, and Ora Engelberg Percus, who taught mathematics at NYU and other institutions. Materials in this collection include correspondence; college and graduate school coursework; research files, including data and calculations; original writings in various stages of completion; teaching files, including course materials and lecture notes; grant proposals and other project files; and conference presentations. Materials documenting Jerome and Ora's original research represent their scholarly outputs, both as individuals and as collaborators who often co-authored work together. This collection also documents Ora Engelberg Percus' experiences as a woman in the male-dominated field of mathematics. Correspondence, resumes, and legal filings document her tenure denial at City College, CUNY's policy in the 1970s of required unpaid maternity leave, her claims of gender discrimination for being dismissed while pregnant, and her participation in the Melani v. CUNY lawsuit. The collection also includes materials documenting Jerome K. Percus' early life, including childhood drawings, photographs, and school yearbooks.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Allon Percus, son of Jerome K. and Ora Engelberg Percus, in March 2023. The accession number associated with this gift is 2023.027. In August 2024, an accretion to this collection was donated by Allon Percus. The accession number associated with this accretion is 2024.064.
Biographical Note of Jerome K. Percus
Jerome K. Percus (1926-2021) was a physicist and mathematician who taught in both the NYU Departments of Mathematics and Physics. Percus was a three-time graduate of Columbia University (B.S. in electrical engineering (1947), M.S. in mathematics (1948), and Ph.D. in physics (1954)), and spent the majority of his academic career at NYU. His research and teaching focused on many-body systems, statistical and mathematical physics, biophysics, chemical physics, and mathematical biology.
Biographical Note of Ora Engelberg Percus
Ora Engelberg Percus (1934-2020) was a mathematician who taught as an adjunct professor in the NYU Department of Mathematics. She graduated from the Hebrew University of Jerusalem with an M.Sc. in Mathematics and Physics (1959) and Columbia University with a Ph.D. in Mathematical Statistics (1965). Ora taught at the University of Tel Aviv, Columbia University's Teachers College, City College (CUNY), and NYU. Ora struggled to secure consistent academic employment due to her gender and pregnancies. Her primary research interests included many-body systems, probability and queueing theory, and random number generators.
Appraisal
The following materials were reviewed, identified as being out of scope for this collection, and not acquired: financial, legal, and medical records (with the exception of materials documenting Ora Engelberg Percus' employment lawsuit); glass slides with biological materials; family medical records; the majority of the Percus' research and subject files, such as reprints, duplicates, referee reports for peer reviewed articles, and grant proposals; correspondence with students about grades and coursework; grade reports for classes taught by Jerome and Ora; and a small amount of lecture notes and original writings on extremely brittle paper.
Materials concerning the Percus' primary interests were prioritized for retention if any annotations or notes were present. These areas for Jerome included many-body systems, statistical and mathematical physics, biophysics, chemical physics, and mathematical biology. These areas for Ora included many-body systems, probability and queueing theory, and random number generators.
Files concerning Ora Engelberg Percus' challenges securing academic work following the birth of her children are retained in this collection, and document a significant experience in her life and career.
One floppy disk was appraised out of the collection due to the presence of student coursework and figures used for Jerome K. Percus' writing that could not be rendered through imaging.
Following digitization in February 2024, glass slides in the collection were discarded as hazardous waste as they contained cellulose nitrate film, a fire safety hazard.
One flash drive containing emails, photographs, and videos was appraised out of the collection because these materials did not relate to Jerome and Ora Engelberg Percus.
Mathematicians; Physicists; Women mathematicians; Mathematics -- Study and teaching; Women in science; Physics -- Study and teaching; Research notes.; Lecture notes.; Research grants.; Administrative records; Percus, Allon; Courant Institute of Mathematical Sciences
- Jerome K. Percus -- Notebooks, 1933, undated (Box 1)
- Jerome K. Percus -- High School and College Notes, 1939-1947 (Box 2)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Naval Training, Notebooks, 1940, undated (Box 3)
- Jerome K. Percus -- College and Graduate School Notes and Exams, 1958-1965 (Box 4)
- Jerome K. Percus -- High School and College Notes; Published Writings, 1943-1953, 2001 (Box 5)
- Jerome K. Percus -- College and Graduate School Notes; Teaching Files, 1953-2016 (Box 6)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Teaching; Writing; Scanning Electron Micoscope (SEM) Research, 1958-2015 (Box 7)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Teaching; Immunology Research and Writing, 1986-2009 (Box 8)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Teaching; Writing, 1962-2016 (Box 9)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Computer Computations; Correspondence; Writing; Lecture Notes, 1956-1959 (Box 10)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Lecture Notes; Writing, 1989-2014 (Box 11)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Correspondence; Notes; Teaching; Writing; Subject Files A-C, 1963-2000 (Box 12)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Subject Files D-J, 1981-1999 (Box 13)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Subject Files K-L, 1981-2006 (Box 14)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Subject Files K-L, 1981-2006 (Box 15)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Subject Files L-O, 1966-2003 (Box 16)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Subject Files O-R, 1980-1999 (Box 17)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Subject Files R-S, 1982-2003 (Box 18)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Subject Files S-T, 1987-2004 (Box 19)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Subject Files W; College and Graduate School Notes; Jerome K. and Ora Engelberg Percus -- Collaborative Projects, 1964-2015 (Box 20)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Subject Files; Jerome K. and Ora Engelberg Percus -- Collaborative Projects, 1965-2009 (Box 21)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Lecture Notes; Writings, 1992-2008 (Box 22)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Lecture Notes; Writings; Prokaryote Class Notes, 2003-2012 (Box 23)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Subject Files B-J, circa 1960s-early 2000s (Box 24)
- Jerome K. and Ora Engelberg Percus -- Research Notes; Writings, 2005-2016 (Box 25)
- Jerome K. and Ora Engelberg Percus -- Research Notes; Writings, 2000-2008 (Box 26)
- Jerome K. and Ora Engelberg Percus -- Correspondence; Research Notes; Writings, 1999-2012 (Box 27)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Research Notes; Lecture Notes; Writings, 1958-2010 (Box 28)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Research Notes; Writings, 2002-2010 (Box 29)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Correspondence; Research Notes; Writings, 2005-2008 (Box 30)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Research Notes; Lecture Notes; Writings (Including Genomics), 2003-2016 (Box 31)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Research Notes; Writings, 1987-1991 (Box 32)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Graduate School Notes; Research Notes; Lecture Notes; Writings, 1947-2000 (Box 33)
- Jerome K. Percus -- College Notes, 1944-1948 (Box 34)
- Jerome K. Percus -- College and Graduate School Notes, 1943-1950 (Box 35)
- Jerome K. Percus -- College Notes; Notebooks, 1944-1964 (Box 36)
- Jerome K. Percus -- College Notes; Notebooks; Article Reprints, 1943-1983 (Box 37)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Lecture Notes; Article Reprints, 1980-2013 (Box 38)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Research Notes; Article Reprints, 1966-2012 (Box 39)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Research Notes; Article Reprints, 1982-2005 (Box 40)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Research Notes; Article Reprints, 2004-2011 (Box 41)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Research Notes; Article Reprints; Lectures at Other Institutions, 1979-2000 (Box 42)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Lecture Notes; Article Reprints; Jerome K. and Ora Engelberg Percus -- Probability Notes, 1995-2007 (Box 43)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Lecture Notes; Article Reprints, 1962-2009 (Box 44)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Research Notes; Article Reprints, 1989-2003 (Box 45)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Research Notes; Article Reprints; Lecture Notes, 2002-2018 (Box 46)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Research Notes; Lecture Notes, 1988-2018 (Box 47)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Research Notes; Lecture Notes, 2002-2020 (Box 48)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Research Notes; Lecture Notes; Article Reprints; Biology Subject Files; Clinical Trial Data, 1991-1996 (Box 49)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Biology and Immunology Subject Files; Writings, 1971-2014 (Box 50)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Biology and Immunology Subject Files; Correspondence; Jerome K. and Ora Engelberg Percus -- Collaborative Writing, 1984-2011 (Box 51)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Biology, Immunology, HIV Subject Files; Jerome K. and Ora Engelberg Percus -- Collaborative Writings, 1987-2001 (Box 52)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Lecture Notes; Writings, 1965-1996 (Box 53)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Lecture Notes, 1971-2010 (Box 54)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Lecture Notes, 1958-1975 (Box 55)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Research Notes; Lecture Notes, 1965-2011 (Box 56)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Research Notes; Article Reprints, 1967-2021 (Box 57)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Research Notes; Correspondence; Article Reprints; Writings, 1985-2002 (Box 58)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Research Notes; Early Writings, 1964-2006 (Box 59)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Research Notes; Article Reprints; Subject Files, 1981-1996 (Box 60)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Research Notes; Writings, 1977-2014 (Box 61)
- Jerome K. and Ora Engelberg Percus -- Research Notes; Writings, 1965-2014 (Box 62)
- Jerome K. and Ora Engelberg Percus -- Research Notes; Writings, 1977-2013 (Box 63)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Research Notes; Article Reprints; Subject Files, 1980-1983 (Box 64)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Lecture Notes; Article Reprints; Writings; Subject Files, 1964-1995 (Box 65)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Research Notes; Genome Grant Files; Subject Files, 1975-2000 (Box 66)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Research Notes; Subject Files; Writings, 1975-2003 (Box 67)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Yearbooks; Commencement Programs; Subject Files, 1941-1997 (Box 68)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Early School Records; CVs and Resumes; Ora Engelberg Percus -- Correspondence; CVs and Resumes, 1935-1992 (Box 69)
- Ora Engelberg Percus -- Correspondence; Project Files; Jerome K. Percus and Ora Engelberg Percus -- Collaborative Writings, 1979-1996 (Box 70)
- Ora Engelberg Percus -- Writings; Jerome K. Percus and Ora Engelberg Percus -- Collaborative Writings, 1988-2001 (Box 71)
- Ora Engelberg Percus -- Research Notes; Project Files; Subject Files; Writings; Jerome K. and Ora Engelberg Percus -- Collaborative Writings, 1985-1991 (Box 72)
- Ora Engelberg Percus -- Research Notes; Subject Files, 1983-1992 (Box 73)
- Ora Engelberg Percus -- Research Notes; Subject Files; Jerome K. and Ora Engelberg Percus -- Collaborative Writings, 1987-2003 (Box 74)
- Ora Engelberg Percus -- Research Notes; Jerome K. Percus -- Research Notes; Subject Files; Writings, 1991-2019 (Box 75)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Research Notes; Lecture Notes; Subject Files; Writings; Jerome K. and Ora Engelberg Percus -- Collaborative Writings, 1989-2009 (Box 76)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Research Notes; Writings; Subject Files, 1975-1999 (Box 77)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Research Notes, 1974-1982 (Box 78)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Research Notes; Writings, circa 1960s-early 2000s (Box 79)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Research Notes; Writings, 1992-1994 (Box 80)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Research Notes; Writings; List of Publications; Ora Engelberg Percus -- Correspondence; Lecture Notes; CVs, 1982-2010 (Box 81)
- Ora Engelberg Percus -- Research Notes; Lecture Notes; Jerome K. and Ora Engelberg Percus -- Collaborative Writings, 1981-1989 (Box 82)
- Ora Engelberg Percus -- Research Notes; Subject Files; Jerome K. and Ora Engelberg Percus -- Collaborative Writings, 1989-2013 (Box 83)
- Ora Engelberg Percus -- Research Notes; Lecture Notes; Jerome K. Percus -- Writings; Jerome K. and Ora Engelberg Percus -- Collaborative Writings, 1990-2002 (Box 84)
- Jerome K. and Ora Engelberg Percus -- Research Notes; Writings, 1970-1989 (Box 85)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Research Notes; Writings, 1993-2006 (Box 86)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Research Notes; Writings; Subject Files, 2008, undated (Box 87)
- Ora Engelberg Percus -- Correspondence; Lecture Notes; Writings; Jerome K. and Ora Engelberg Percus -- Collaborative Writings, 1991-2017 (Box 88)
- Ora Engelberg Percus -- Research Notes; Lecture Notes; Writings, 1994-1999 (Box 89)
- Ora Engelberg Percus -- Research Notes; Project Files, 1970-1995 (Box 90)
- Ora Engelberg Percus -- Research Notes; Jerome K. Percus -- Writings, 1984-2001 (Box 91)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Research Notes; Writings, 1993, undated (Box 92)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Research Notes, 1990, undated (Box 93)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Research Notes; Writings; Jerome K. and Ora Engelberg Percus -- Collaborative Writings, 1982-1991 (Box 94)
- Ora Engelberg Percus -- Correspondence; Graduate School Notes and Notebooks; Writings, 1960-1996 (Box 95)
- Ora Engelberg Percus -- Graduate School Notes and Notebooks, 1960-1963 (Box 96)
- Ora Engelberg Percus -- Graduate School Notes and Notebooks; Research Notes, 1961-1964 (Box 97)
- Ora Engelberg Percus -- Graduate School Notes and Notebooks; Jerome K. Percus -- Research Notes; Writings, 1961-1980 (Box 98)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Research Notes; Writings, 1966, undated (Box 99)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Research Notes; Lecture Notes; Jerome K. and Ora Engelberg Percus -- Collaborative Research and Writing on Queues, 1964-1981 (Box 100)
- Ora Engelberg Percus -- Correspondence; Graduate School Notes and Notebooks; Writings, 1965-1987 (Box 101)
- Ora Engelberg Percus -- Graduate School Notes; Tenure Case; Jerome K. and Ora Engelberg Percus -- Research Notes; Writings, 1965-2012 (Box 102)
- Ora Engelberg Percus -- Tenure Case; Discrimination Complaint; Melani v. CUNY Lawsuit, 1967-1976 (Box 103)
- Ora Engelberg Percus -- Research Notes; Graduate School Notes and Notebooks, circa 1950s-1960s (Box 104)
- Ora Engelberg Percus -- Graduate School Notes and Notebooks; Jerome K. Percus -- Conference Proceedings, circa 1950s-1960s, undated (Box 105)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Conference Proceedings, undated (Box 106)
- Ora Engelberg Percus -- Research Notes; Graduate School Notes; Writings; Jerome K. Percus -- Research Notes; Princeton Researcher Collaboration, circa 1950s-1993 (Box 107)
- Ora Engelberg Percus -- Lecture Notes, 1965-1972 (Box 108)
- Ora Engelberg Percus -- Lecture Notes; Jerome K. Percus -- Research Notes, 1960-1972 (Box 109)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Research Notes, undated (Box 110)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Research Notes; Photograph Scrapbook; Ora Engelberg Percus -- Research Notes, 1964-2018 (Box 111)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Drawings; Portrait; Diploma; Notebook, 1939-1947 (Box 112)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Naval Training Photograph, 1944 (Box Shared University Archives 097, Folder 10)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Diplomas, 1941-1949 (Box Shared University Archives 097, Folder 11)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Glass Slides, New York and Washington, D.C., 1955-1956; cuid18373
  Appraisal
  Following digitization in February 2024, the original slides were discarded as hazardous waste as they contained cellulose nitrate film, a fire safety hazard.
- Jerome K. Percus -- "Dr. Erick Martz Cell Division 1 type", undated; cuid18596 (Box Shared University Archives 017, 16mm film reels 364.0001)
- Jerome K. Percus -- "Garrod SO (2 Films)", undated; cuid18597 (Box Shared University Archives 014, 16mm film reels 364.0002)
- Jerome K. Percus -- "(Original!) Fig. 1 Sternberg and Garrod - sorting out in monolayer", undated; cuid18598 (Box Shared University Archives 014, 16mm film reels 364.0003)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Untitled Film Reel, undated; cuid18599 (Box Shared University Archives 017, 16mm film reels 364.0004)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Research Notes, 2013-2014 (Box 113)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Physics Department Meeting Minutes; Research Notes and Materials, 1974-2016 (Box 114)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Correspondence; Research Notes and Materials; Course Lecture Notes, 1964-1994 (Box 115)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Research Materials; Course Lecture Notes; Exams; Homework Assignments; Course Syllabi, 1954-2006 (Box 116)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Exams; Homework Assignments; Course Syllabi; Lecture Notes; Correspondence, 1969-2009 (Box 117)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Course Lecture Notes; Exams, 1969-2007 (Box 118)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Exams; Course Lecture Notes; Homework Assignments; Research Materials; Drafts and Published Articles, 1969-2002 (Box 119)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Research Notes, circa 1980s (Box 120)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Research Notes; Exams; Course Notes; Homework Assignments, 1963-2011 (Box 121)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Course Lecture Notes; Exams; Homework Assignments, 1968-2007 (Box 122)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Course Lecture Notes; Correspondence; Conference Materials; Published Articles; NYU Directories, 1968-2005 (Box 123)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Course Lecture Notes; Homework Assignments; Conference Materials, 1963-2015 (Box 124)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Conference Materials, 1976-2010 (Box 125)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Course Lecture Notes; Memoranda; Exams, 1969-2000 (Box 126)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Course Lecture Notes; Exams; Grant Applications; Conference Materials; Correspondence, 1957-1990 (Box 127)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Course Lecture Notes, 1965-2016 (Box 128)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Course Lecture Notes; Research Materials; Memorandum; Conference Materials; Correspondence, 1968-2009 (Box 129)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Correspondence; Research Notes; Course Lecture Notes; Grant Proposals, 1978-1999 (Box 130)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Bound Article; Research Notes; Course Lecture Notes, 1968-2002 (Box 131)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Course Lecture Notes, 1954-2011 (Box 132)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Course Lecture Notes; Article Drafts; Research Notes, undated (Box 133)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Research Notes, undated (Box 134)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Research Notes; Technical Reports; Correspondence; NYU Research Journals, 1958-2008 (Box 135)
- Jerome K. Percus -- CISM Research Abstracts; Research Grant Proposals, 1984-2007 (Box 136)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Research Grant Proposals; Correspondence, 1976-2000 (Box 137)
- Jerome K. Percus -- NYU Resources; Correspondence; Research Notes; Published Articles, 1965-2011 (Box 138)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Memoranda; Correspondence; Conference Materials; Exams, 1962-2004 (Box 139)
- Jerome K. Percus -- Research Grant Proposals; Course Lecture Notes; Research Materials; Memorandum, 1954-2016 (Box 140)